Guide to the Carl Geiser Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War ALBA.AUDIO.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Geiser Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War
1977-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Geiser, Carl
ALBA.AUDIO.004
0.8 Linear Feet in 1 card box and 1 box
35 audiocassettes
11 sound discs (cd)
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He fought with the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War as a member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and was taken prisoner and held in a fascist prisoner of war camp for a year before being released in April 1939. After a career as an aeronautical engineer, he retired in 1971 and began to research and write a history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. His book, Prisoners of the Good Fight: The Spanish Civil War 1936-1939, was published in 1986. The Carl Geiser Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War consist of 35 audiocassettes, most of them interviews with former prisoners conducted as part of the research for Geiser's book. Also included are recordings of Geiser discussing trips to Cuba and Spain.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2001.210 and 2001.111.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by the narrator's last name.
Biographical Note
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He was the oldest of six children; his father, a farmer, died in the influenza epidemic at the end of World War I, and his mother a year later of tuberculosis. His maternal grandparents, Swiss immigrants who spoke little English, raised Geiser and his siblings. The young Geiser received his primary education in a one-room schoolhouse while helping to tend the family's sixteen-acre farm. Upon his graduation from Orrville High School in 1928, he enrolled in the YMCA School of Technology (later Fenn College) in Cleveland, where he majored in electrical engineering.
In 1932, following the establishment of diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet Union, Geiser was part of the first National Student Federation mission to travel to the newly recognized country. Impressed by the Soviet system and the tenets of socialist ideology, Geiser joined the Young Communist League on his return to Ohio. He was active in the American Student Union in Cleveland and served as a delegate to the First Student Congress Against War and Fascism held in Chicago. It was there that Geiser met his future wife Sylvia, a teacher and organizer who shared his political fervor. The couple moved to New York where they were absorbed into a dynamic culture of political activism and organizing. Geiser wrote press releases and edited International Labor Defense bulletins, organized for the League against War and Fascism, and in 1936 was elected to the National Committee of the Young Communist League.
On April 13, 1937 Geiser boarded the S.S. Georgic to join the International Brigades massing in defense of the Spanish Republic. He served as an ammunition carrier at the Battle of Brunete, saw action at Quinto, and advanced to the rank of Lieutenant and then Political Commissar. Wounded at the conflict at Fuentes de Ebro, Geiser was hospitalized for three months. Returned to the front as Commissar of the Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion in January 1938, he was captured by fascist forces on April 1, 1938. For the next year, he was interned at San Pedro de Cardeña, along with over 650 International Brigades prisoners. Through the efforts of the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the U.S. State Department, Geiser and a group of 71 Americans were released in April 1939.
Geiser returned to New York and secured an engineering position with Liquidometer, a manufacturer of aeronautic equipment. By the early 1970s, Geiser turned his attention once more to Spain. Upon retirement at age 71, Geiser began to write a comprehensive history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. With the assistance of fellow prisoner Robert Steck, Geiser amassed biographical information on the 120 Americans incarcerated in Spanish prisons. He also corresponded with over 150 veterans worldwide to solicit their reminiscences, and traveled to archives in the United States and Europe to conduct research. Five years of research and writing culminated in the publication of Prisoners of the Good Fight (Lawrence Hill and Co., 1986).
Custodial History
The Carl Geiser Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War were donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Geiser in 1986 as part of the Carl Geiser Papers. Additional materials were given in 1990. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Geiser Papers (ALBA 004) ALBA Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2) Robert Steck Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War (ALBA AUDIO 104) Robert Steck Papers (ALBA 104) Randall Smith: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Historical Commission Records (ALBA 003)
Scope and Content Note
The Carl Geiser Audio Recordings on Spanish Civil War Prisoners of War consist of 35 audio recordings created by Geiser in the course of research for his book, Prisoners of the Good Fight. The collection dates from the 1970s and 1980s and the bulk of the material is interviews with former prisoners of war conducted as part of the research for Geiser's book. Also included are recordings of Geiser discussing trips he took to Cuba and Spain.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access CDs for some audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Other audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Audiocassettes.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Alexander, William, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 001)
- Allen, Richard Sanders, 1981-04-13 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 002)
- Amatniek, Ernest, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 003)
- Clemente Garcia, Santos; Hans Streuli (translation of a German letter), undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 004)
- Eggar, Dougal, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 005)
- Ersler, Gabriel, 1983-09-19-1983-09-23 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 006)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Trip to Cuba, 1982 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 033, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Spain (tape 1 of 2), June 8 - June 10 (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 034)
- Geiser, Carl; Reflections on Spain (tape 2 of 2) [from Madrid], undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 035)
- Gilbert, Tony, 1986-09-10 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 007)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 1 of 3), 1981-07-20 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 008)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 2 of 3), 1981-07-20 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 009)
- Hafner, Otto (tape 3 of 3), 1981-07-20 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 010)
- Heinzman, Georg; Karl Loesch, 1981 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 011)
- Herman, Joe Hy, 1978-05-03 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 012)
- Interview with an Italian Woman re: Italian POWS Held by Republican Army, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 032)
- Jones, Tom, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 013)
- Kowalski, Arthur, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 014)
- Levitas, Maurice; Tom Jones (tape 2 of 2; related to tape 004-013 or 004-028?), undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004-015)
  Levitas, Ruth
- Loesch, Karl, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 016)
- Lopez, Jules Herman (Cintron); Hy Wallach; Joseph Lafayette Young, 1977-07-31 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 017, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
  Wallach, Nancy
- Lopez, Jules Herman (Cintron); Hy Wallach; Joseph Lafayette Young (committee meeting), 1978-09-17 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 018, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Moon, Jimmy, August 15 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 019)
- Moon, Jimmy, September 12 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 020)
- Nelson, Steve; Jules Paivio (Nelson's greetings to the Mac Paps), October 1977 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 021)
- Ornitz, Louis Noah (tape 1 of 2), 1982-01-07 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 022)
- Ornitz, Louis Noah (tape 2 of 2), 1982-01-07 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 023)
- Riffe, Carl Herman, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 024)
- Riffe, Carl Herman; Velmar Edward Hodge, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 025)
- Streit, Herman (side 1); first meeting with Anti. Wider. Kom [Antifascist Historical Committee], Berlin (side 2) (tape 1 of 2), undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 026)
- Streit, Herman (tape 2 of 2), undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 027)
- Tenor, Leon; Maurice Levitas, August 30 (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 028)
- West, Frank; Documents on Prisoners at San Pedro de Cardena, undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 029)
- West, Frank, undated (Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 030)
- Young, Joseph Lafayette, 1977-07-31 (Box Shared Tamiment 077, Cassette 004- 031)